Finding Aid for Sandra S. Cole papers, 1994-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sandra S. Cole papers 1994-2007
Cole, Sandra S., 1937-
1.5 linear feet
2010156 Aa 2
Sandra S. Cole is a sexologist and professor (retired) at the University of Michigan School of Medicine. This collection documents Cole’s transgender advocacy, including the University of Michigan’s Comprehensive Gender Services Program, the inclusion of gender identity in the non-discrimination policies of the University of Michigan and the City of Ann Arbor, and her presentations, public appearances, and consultation work on transgender issues in the late 1990s and early 2000s.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Sandra S. Cole (donor no. 10378 ) in July, 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Sandra S. Cole, Ph.D., is a professor (retired), sexologist and sex educator. From 1970 to 1977, she was on the faculty of the University of Minnesota Medical School, in the Program in Human Sexuality. In 1977, she joined the Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation at the University of Michigan School of Medicine. In 1993 she founded the University's Comprehensive Gender Services Program (CGSP), a multidisciplinary healthcare program for transgender people. She served as the program's director until her retirement in 2000.
Since the early 1980s, Cole has been active in the transgender community as an educator, consultant, and advocate. She was the co-author of Ann Arbor, Michigan's ordinance on gender identity non-discrimination, which was passed in 1999. Between 1999 and 2007 she worked for the inclusion of gender identity in the University's non-discrimination policies. Also active in this effort were Jim Toy from the Office of Equity and Diversity, Royster Harper, Vice President for Student Affairs, Frederic McDonald-Dennis, Director of the Office of Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Affairs, and others.
The Sandra S. Cole papers document Cole's work on behalf of the transgender community at the University of Michigan and in Ann Arbor. A number of the papers in the collection are photocopies of items held by the Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction at Indiana University. The collection consists of four series: Comprehensive Gender Services Program, University of Michigan Non-Discrimination Policy, Lectures, Public Appearances, and Consultation Work, and Transgender Reference Materials.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Cole, Sandra S., 1937-; Sex discrimination--Law and legislation.; Sex discrimination in education--Michigan.; Transgender people--Legal status, laws, etc.--Michigan.; Transgender people--Medical care--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Comprehensive Gender Services Program (CGSP), 1997-2000
  The bulk of the Comprehensive Gender Services Program series consists of a 1997 annual report on the program's services, policies, and procedures. The series also includes program evaluation forms, mission and vision statements, and miscellaneous forms and procedures dating from 1998 to 2000.
  - Annual Report, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Forms and Program Information, 1998-2000 and undated (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Non-Discrimination Policy, 1999-2007
  The second series, University of Michigan Non-Discrimination Policy, documents the history of transgender advocacy at the University of Michigan. Materials include reports from the Gender Identity Working Group in 2003 and the Task Force on the Campus Climate for Transgender, Bisexual, Lesbian, and Gay (TBLG) Faculty, Staff, and Students in 2004-2005. The work of these groups helped lay the groundwork for the changes in the University's non-discrimination policy that were passed in 2007. This series also includes Cole's notes, correspondence, and prepared remarks for meetings with the Regents of the University in 2005 and 2007.
  - Reports and Memoranda on Transgender Advocacy at U of M, 1999-2002 and undated (Box 1)
  - Annotated Draft of Standard Practice Guide, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Division of Student Affairs Gender Identity Services Survey Results, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Gender Identity Working Group Agenda, Minutes, and Reports, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Task Force on the Campus Climate for TBLG Faculty Staff, and Students Reports and Related Materials, 2004 (Box 1)
  - TBLG Subcommittee Reports, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Notes and Correspondence, 2005 and undated (Box 1)
  - Regents Meeting Comments, Correspondence, and Related Materials, 2003 and 2005 (Box 1)
    (includes biographical sketches of Cole)
  - Amendment to Regents Bylaws, Correspondence, Clippings, and Related Materials, 2007 (Box 1)
- Lectures, Public Appearances, and Consultation, 1997-2004
  Lectures, Public Appearances, and Consultation documents Cole's role as an advocate, educator, and consultant on transgender issues. Materials include policy drafts and comments related to the 1999 passage of the Ann Arbor City Ordinance Amendment; lecture notes, presentation slides, and reference materials for lectures on transgender identity and healthcare; and reports and articles from the Open Justice Commission on sexual orientation and transgender education for the legal community.
  - Michigan Model: Drafts, Lecture Notes, and Slide Printouts, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality Healing Workshop: Notes and Correspondence, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor City Council Ordinance Amendment Drafts, Comments, Clippings, and Related Material, 1999 (Box 1)
  - U of M Sexual Harassment Training Agenda and Notes, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Transgender Odyssey Toward Acceptance: Slide Printouts, Lecture Notes, and Related Materials, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
    (includes biographical sketch of Cole)
  - Transgender Odyssey Toward Acceptance: Notes, Slides, and Transparencies, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Open Justice Commission Reports, Articles, and Related Materials, 2002-2003, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - The Avalanche: Lecture Notes and Related Materials, 2003 (Box 1)
  - National Transgender Library and Archives Dedication Correspondence and Remarks, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Transgender Healthcare: Lecture Notes and Related Materials, ca. 2000 (Box 1)
- Transgender Reference Materials, 1994-2007
  The final series, Transgender Reference Materials, consists of articles and clippings on topics related to transgender identity and social experience, non-discrimination policies, civil rights, and healthcare.
  - Civil Rights and Legal Resources for Transgender, 1998-2003 and undated (Box 2)
  - College and University Non-Discrimination Policies, 1994-2007 (Box 2)
  - Gender Identity Disorder/Gender Dysphoria, Articles and Related Materials, 1996-1997 and undated (Box 2)
  - Transgender College Faculty and Students, Articles and Clippings, 1994-2004 (Box 2)
  - Transgender Healthcare, Articles and Bulletins, 1995-1997 and undated (Box 2)
  - Transgender Identity, Articles, Clippings, and Related Materials, 1999-2004 (Box 2)
  - Transgender Medical and Social Services Brochures, ca. 2000 (Box 2)
Related Material
Sandra Cole has donated the bulk of her professional papers to the Kinsey Institute for Research in Sex, Gender, and Reproduction at Indiana University.